托马斯爵士
Sir Thomas.
有何消息
What's the news?
那些世事如同疟疾
This matter hangs like a fever
时好时坏
one day good, another bad.
吾王以许诺宽恕与惩罚恩威并施 加之王室军威的重压
With the promise of a pardon, and the threat of an advancing royal army,
林肯郡叛军业已遣散回家
the rebels in Lincolnshire have dispersed and gone home.
约克郡呢
And in Yorkshire?
在约克郡以及整个北部地区
In Yorkshire and the whole North we are facing
我们面临前所未有的威胁
the most dangerous insurrection that has ever been seen.
叛军3天前攻占了约克郡
The rebels entered the town of York three days ago
叛军大肆庆祝 有人说他们即将向南部挺进
and celebrated mass in the cathedral; some say they intend to march South.
"吾王陛下
"Your Majesty,
"臣有急情告禀
I write to you on an urgent matter.
"流言传说 求恩叛军已逼近臣据守之庞蒂弗拉克特城堡
"We've had word that a pilgrim army is marching"on to Pontefract Castle, which is under my command.
"恕臣直言 如无援军 我等将无力抵御叛军
"I am compelled to tell you that I can't defend this castle"without more soldiers and arms.
"作为东部边陲守卫者
"As the warden of the East Marches
"及陛下枢密院忠实成员
and a loyal member"of Your Majesty's council
"臣伏祈陛下与'求恩者'开端谈判
"I beg Your Majesty to consider negotiating with these pilgrims.
"吾王麾下谦卑忠仆达西叩上"
I remain your humble and obedient servant. Darcy."
那是什么 你发现了什么
What is it? What have you found?
小块碎骨 陛下
A splinter of bone, Your Majesty.
你曾经说不过是伤口溃疡 很容易治愈
You told me before it was an ulcer. That it was easily cured!
- 像这样的伤势… 陛下 - 上帝啊
- A wound like this, Your Majesty... - Jesus Christ!
其实你根本就不懂 对吗
You don't know what it is, do you? Do you?
陛下切莫担心 小人将施以泥敷剂
Your Majesty must not be alarmed. We shall apply a poultice to draw
取出伤口表面其他碎骨
any more splinters to the surface.
然后另寻良方一劳永逸治愈陛下伤势
Then we shall look to other remedies to heal permanently Your Majesty's wound.
你对我就像一个傻瓜一样
You treat me like a fool.
你们这些对我都像傻瓜一样
Everyone here treats me like a fool.
滚出去
Get out.
- 给我滚出去 - 陛下…
- Get out! - Majesty...
唧唧歪歪的江湖郎中
You're quacks and charlatans.
不如我自己来另寻良方
I will find my own remedies.
公爵大人
Your Grace.
大人
My Lord,
我前来取你所应允准备的军火枪炮
I was promised artillery when I arrived here.
但我未见任何枪械
But I don't see any guns.
大人 我们有枪械
Your Grace, we have guns
但我们尚未找妥运送枪械之马匹
but we have not been unable to find any horses or drays to transport them.
也许您还未明白
Perhaps you don't understand.
我此番前来所为国王最紧急事务
I am about the King's most urgent business.
如果区区马匹你都不能为国王征调
And if you cannot commandeer some horses for his Majesty's use then
你怎配伦敦市长之职
how can you call yourself Mayor of London?
大人 在下不想强行征用民众马匹而引发恐慌
Your Grace, I did not want to produce panic by forcing people to part with their horses or drays.
白痴
IDIOT!
我命令你亲自在两日之内找齐所需马匹
I charge you personally to find enough horses within two days
将枪械运至我军
and bring the guns on after our army
否则定然唯你是问
or God help me I will hold you to account.
你自求多福吧 市长大人
With any luck, Mr. Mayor,
可别让我有机会把你送上刑场开膛破肚
I will afterwards get the chance to see you disemboweled at Tyburn!
- 洛克福特女士 - 王后
- Lady Rochford? - Madam,
陛下仍需遵医嘱待在寝
the King is still confined to his chambers by his physicians' orders,
但转致歉意并望您安好
but sends his regrets and hopes you are well.
我很为他担忧 特别在如此情形之下
I worry for him so much. Especially at such a time.
陛下所忧极是
Your Majesty is right to do so.
这些叛军都是彻头彻尾的恶棍
These rebels are nothing but villains.
他们是被蛊惑的信徒
They are totally alienated from true religion.
他们会用武力使我们回到
They want to take us back to the dark days
黑暗的无知迷信年代
of ignorance and superstition. And by force!
- 我希望此事很快就可平定 - 是的
- I hope to God they will soon be overcome. - Yes.
洛克福特女士 我要你替我办件事
Lady Rochford,I have something I wish you to arrange for me.
我相信此事会让吾王万分欢愉
I'm sure it will give the King a great deal of pleasure.
(庞蒂弗拉克特城堡 约克郡 英格兰北部)
上帝啊 达西大人
My God, Lord Darcy.
多么骇人的情景啊
What a sight is there!
平民聚众反叛吾王 不以大打旗号为耻
Arrant rebels against the King's Majesty brazenly bearing their badges of shame!
他们的确如此 主教大人
Indeed so, Your Grace.
我也没想到在我有生之年能目睹此等光景
I never thought in all my long days to see such a sight.
大人意欲何为 向他们开火吗
What are you going to do? Fire on them?
你知道的很清楚我几乎没几只枪炮可用
You know very well I have almost no useful guns.
可您同样可以关门御敌
You could resist them all the same, and close your gates.
毕竟此乃国王谕令
After all those are the King's orders.
有鉴于此 我想最好是先礼后兵举行对话
As to that, I think it better to talk to them first,
他们既是英国同胞 也是主内肢体
as fellow Englishmen and fellow Christians.
我将在门厅与他们首领会面
I'll meet their leaders in the gatehouses,
在城堡墙外
outside the castle walls.
卫兵
Guards!
达西大人
My Lord Darcy,
主教大人
Your Grace,
我们抱着和平的诚意前来
we come here in peace.
阿斯克先生 身为国王代表
Mr. Aske.As the King's representative
我拥有对付你等之武力 可以重挫你等
I have the means hereto hinder you and to do some injury to your cause.
大人 我等求恩巡礼初衷乃出于共善
My Lord, we have embarked upon this Pilgrimage of Grace for the common good,
为了上帝的爱 我们希望恢复神圣教堂 维护信仰
for the love we bear to God's faith,our Holy Church and the maintenance of it,
为维护我们至尊国王的在世权柄
for the preservation of our sovereign King
为了清除那些血腥的罪恶官吏们
and the expulsion of villain's blood and evil councilors.
我们意欲向国王陛下请愿
We mean to petition the King's highness
促使停止对修道院的恶意毁灭与亵渎
to stop the woeful destruction of our monasteries and abbeys.
阿斯克先生 你宣称忠于国王
Master Aske, you claim to be loyal to the King
而你的实际行动却在反叛违背国王的权威
but your very actions defy and deny the King's supremacy!
非也 大主教大人
Lord Archbishop,
王国之内 无人比我更忠于吾王
there is no man now alive in England more loyal to the King than I am.
假以时日 我将证明我的忠心
I trust in time to prove it.
我们的起事之矛头所在并非吾王 只是意在清君侧
Our quarrel lies not with him, but onlywith those close to him.
你说的天花乱坠 你这位高权重之辈更该受到谴责
It's very well for you to sound so high and mighty, but you and your kind are also to blame
因为你不曾向国王建忠言
for not advising the King honestly
也不揭露这些异端恶行横行 这才是真正对国王之大不敬
about the spread of heresy and abuse throughout his kingdom.
克伦威尔与克朗默之流之恶行与亵渎
For what are Cromwell and Cranmer but heretics
才是真正侵害王国之共善
and manifest abusers of this commonwealth?
达西大人
Lord Darcy,
如我所言 我们无意伤害任何人
as I told you we mean no displeasure to any person.
我们但求一住所和前进通道
We ask for shelter and free passage.
我们此举乃是求恩 其承载着对上帝的誓言
All our pilgrims have taken an oath
勿因嫉恨而行罪恶奴役或屠戮
not to slay or murder out of envy,
但为了天下共善抛却了恐惧
but to put away fear for the commonwealth
高举着基督十字架与他们内心的信仰勇往直前
and march with the cross of Christand their heart's faith before them.
如果你试图阻止我们
But we will fight and die
我们将誓死战斗到底
if you seek to stop us.
我想让你负责本城的防御
I am putting you in charge of the defenses here the city.
可以设法强征些新丁
We shall need to organize new levies.
给所有的士绅大人们传令备战
Send word to every lords and gentlemen to be ready with his power.
你可随意向从伦敦塔索取所需军火物质
Take all the weapons,harness and ordnance you need from the Tower.
如果需要 就尽管去购置更多军火
Buy more if you need to from the merchants in the city.
确实如此 我们目前很麻烦
Then it's true. We are in trouble.
白痴
IDIOT
克伦威尔先生
Mr. Cromwell,
陛下召见您
His Majesty will receive you now.
我刚收到达西大人的信件
I've just received a letter from Lord Darcy.
他说叛军力量强大 他无法抵挡
He says that he is in great danger from the rebels and cannot maintain his resistance.
虽然如此 他控制着一个城堡 重要强大的关卡
And yet he holds a castle. A great stronghold.
难道那不意味着他可以抵挡住叛军吗？
Does he not mean to stand firm against these traitors?
陛下 我刚刚得知
Your Majesty, I've just been told
一股数目庞大的叛军人马已经进入庞蒂弗拉克特城
that the rebels have already entered the town of Pontefract with overwhelming numbers.
克伦威尔先生
Mr. Cromwell...
庞蒂弗拉克特城堡乃是南北之门户所在
Pontefract is the gateway to the South.
具有重大战略重要性
It has great strategic importance.
你立刻写信给达西大人
You will write a letter to Lord Darcy at once.
你告诉他 我要他守住城堡
You will tell him that I expect him to hold that castle
不惜任何代价
at all costs!
遵命 陛下
Yes, Your Majesty.
王室军队是什么情形 他们是否在粉碎叛军战斗中
And what of the royal army?What are they doing to crush this rebellion?
沙福克公爵大人现在何方
Where is his Grace the Duke of Suffolk?
还有那个混蛋什鲁斯伯里 我曾对他三令五申
And that bastard Shrewsbury! I told him too!
上帝啊 这些人都在做什么啊
What in God's name are these men doing?
先生们
Gentlenman
- 约克郡的朋友们 - 达西大人
- Friends of York. Lord Darcy. - My Lord!
阁下
My lord.
达西和约克郡背叛了我？
Darcy and York have betrayed me?
我倒要看看他们还会到何等地步
Well, we shall see what end they come to!
为何什鲁斯伯里和沙福克公爵尚未发动进攻？
And why haven't Shrewsbury and Suffolk attacked yet?
我听到的只有抱怨和借口
All I hear are their complaints and their excuses!
你们知道我怎么想吗
You know what I think?
我想他们开始就连自己的影子都害怕
I think they have become afraid of their own shadows!
我要御驾亲征北部地区
I have a mind to go North myself.
我来领军
I'll lead the army!
我要亲自给这些混蛋和叛军血的教训 大开杀戒
I'll teach these bastard ingrates and rebels a fearful bloody lesson in slaughter!
我希望陛下不是真的要亲自领军
I wish Your Majesty would not consider doing so.
为什么
Why?
你以为我太虚弱？
Do you suppose I'm too feeble?
陛下千金之躯 何苦涉险与这些低贱平民叛乱之中
I meant that Your Majesty's life is far too precious to be put at risk against such a common rabble.
当然 如果您前去 一定如猛虎入狼群
Of course if you chose to go, you would be like a lion among wolves.
弗兰西斯爵士 我并不需要你来奉承我
Sir Francis, I don't require you to flatter me.
不敢 陛下
No, Your Majesty.
给沙福克公爵发一份直接了当的信息
Send a plain message to Suffolk.
质问他们为什么违背我的命令
Ask him why he refuses to obey my commands
问他是否是个懦夫
and ask him if he is a coward.
- 遵命 陛下 - 克伦威尔先生
- Majesty. - And Mr. Cromwell!
如果事情恶化 我很了解谁该被问罪
If things go badly, I know well enough who to blame.
陛下 我能做什么来减轻您的痛苦吗
Can I get Your Majesty anything for your pain?
当然 我相信你可以
Yes, I believe you can.
(纽瓦克农场 布兰顿总部)
公爵大人 什鲁斯伯里伯爵驾到
Your Grace, the Earl of Shrewsbury is here.
- 大人 - 公爵大人
- My Lord. - Your Grace.
- 解散 - 大人 - 大人
- Men dismissed. - Your Grace. - Your Grace
我们深陷困境 大人
We meet at a desperate moment, my Lord.
我们要对付的不仅是叛军强盛
Not only are the rebel forces overwhelmingly strong against us,
而且军心不齐
but those men I do have I cannot altogether trust.
许多士兵相信叛军是义举而且符合上帝意愿
Many of them I swear think the rebels' quarrels to be good and godly.
国王仍然催促我们尽快出击
Still, the King has urged us to attack as soon as possible.
如果陛下亲眼目睹现状将不会如此
His Majesty would not do so if he saw our plight with his own eyes.
我们几乎没有马夫 敌众我寡
I have almost no horsemen,and those I do have are rather the flower of the North.
我无法去发动一场注定失败的攻击
It is not possible your lordship to give battle knowing defeat to be a certainty.
- 你有其他计划吗 - 我只能和他们谈判 - 谈判？
- Do you have some other plan? - I intend to parley with them.- Parley?
大人 我们首要任务是防止他们逃窜并向南部进军
My Lord,it's our first duty to stop them escaping and marching South.
如果在谈判 他们就不会进军
If they are talking they are not marching.
那么你去跟国王说
Then you must tell the King.
什鲁斯伯里的军队在这里
Shrewsbury's forces are here...
沙福克公爵在这里 离纽瓦克不远
Suffolk's here, not far from Newark.
看起来他们最初的企图是控制住沿着特伦特河的这条防线
It seems likely that they had originally planned to hold a line here, along the River Trent,
阻挡我们向南部进军
to block our advance southwards.
他们有多少人
How strong are they?
- 什鲁斯伯里有多少人？六千？- 对
- We think that Shrewsbury's men are 6000? - Right.
沙福克人数更少
Suffolk's a lot less.
他们也都缺少马匹和大炮
They also lack horse and cannon.
那我们有多少人
And how many are we?
- 据我统计 超过三万 - 三万？
- By my reckoning,somewhere over thirty thousand. - Thirty Thousand?
我们在这里 在邓卡斯特有大量人马
We have kept large forces here at Doncaster,
在杰福克斯修道院
at Jervaux Abbey
而且我们目前包围了坎伯兰郡伯爵的斯基普顿城堡
and we are presently laying siegeto the Earl of Cumberland's castle at Skipton.
在顿河北部 我们基本完成了对乡村的控制
North of the River Don, we have almost complete control of the country.
让他们朝我们进军吧
Let them come on to us!
有上帝在我们这一边 阿斯克先生
With God on our side, Mr. Aske,
我们必胜无疑
we shall prevail.
真不幸啊 陛下
Poor you, Your Majesty.
抹些药膏
Pour the ointment over it.
- 味道像酸模 亚麻子？- 是药用植物
- I smell sorrel and...linseed? - Meadowplant,
碎珍珠粉 芸香和其他东西
crushed pearls, herb of grace, other things.
我不再信任那个医生 我只得自寻良方
I concocted it myself. I don't trust my physicians.
挺住
Hold still!
你非常勇敢 米塞尔登女士
You're very brave, Lady Misseldon.
勇敢胜过我的将军们
Braver, I think, than my Captains.
但更加美丽
And much more beautiful.
好了 撒上了 相信陛下会爽些了
There, it's done. I trust Your Majesty is more comfortable.
陛下希望我留下来吗？
Does Your Majesty wish me to stay?
指望英格兰国王会认识到自己的错误
It seems we were wrong to suppose that the King of England
与其对灵魂的危险看起来是个错误的想法
would realize his mistakes and the dangers to his soul.
他反而还在继续支持克伦威尔
Instead he continues to encourage Cromwel
大肆破坏亵渎教堂 掠夺教会财物
to vandalize and defile the houses of God and steal their treasures,
仅仅出乎个人用途和喜好
all for his own use and pleasure.
不过即使黑暗之中 也有一丝亮光
And yet, even in the darkness there is a light.
我是说 信徒的起义非常伟大
I mean, this great uprising of the faithful.
- 求恩巡礼 - 我也有所耳闻
- This Pilgrimage of Grace. - I have heard of it too.
求恩者们打着耶稣基督的旗帜进军
The pilgrims who marched beneath the banner of Christ.
圣父要你就此写个英文小册子
The Holy Father asks you to write a pamphlet in English
指责国王与其顾问们为异教徒
denouncing the King and his advisors as heretics.
一定 我这就去动手
Of course. I will start work on it straight away.
先别 等等
No, No. Wait, wait.
圣父对你期盼良多 绝非仅仅你的署名
His Holiness needs more from you than just your signature.
在我的举荐下 教皇已决定任命你为官方使节
With my encouragement, he has decided to appoint you an official legate.
你将前去法国以及其他国家
You will travel to France and to the Low Countries
会见皇帝与王公们的代表
and meet representatives of the King and the Emperor.
- 主教大人 - 你要游说他们提供资金 武器和雇佣兵等
- Eminence...? - You will persuade them to provide monies, arms and mercenaries
来支援英国这次神圣的宗教圣战
to support this most Holy Crusade in England.
如果这是教皇交给我的任务
If that is what His Holiness asks me to do,
当然我会尽心完成
then of course I will do it,
就如同像孝子侍奉父亲
like an obedient son to a father.
教皇陛下已经恩准册封你为红衣主教
His Holiness has agreed to make you a Cardinal.
此乃您的红衣主教方型帽
And here is your biretta.
我不能接受
I cannot accept.
为何不
Why not?
我不够格
I'm not worthy.
换句话说 你宁可相信自己的判断高于圣父 教皇陛下
In other words, you prefer your own judgment to that of the Pope, your Holy Father.
无疑您此举本想显示谦卑
No doubt you suppose that makes you seem humble.
那却会成为对教皇傲慢之罪过 波尔神父
But actually it is the sin of pride for the Pope.
沙福克公爵大人禀告他别无选择 只得暂时与叛军周旋
His Grace informs Your Majesty he has no choice in the matter but to treat with them...
他本欲对参与其事的当地士绅以叛乱治罪
In so doing, he hopes to bring the nobles and the gentry to treachery
但囿于目前情势只能恩泽广施实行宽恕
and for their own sakes and their own interestst hey will disown the commons,
就如同林肯郡的方式一样
if promised a pardon as in fact happened in Lincolnshire.
他们不该被宽恕
They are not all to be pardoned.
头领不在内 永远不宽恕那些头领
Not the leaders. Never the leaders.
沙福克公爵都开了些什么条件放他们回家
But what terms does my Lord Suffolk intend to offer the commons to make them go home?
公爵大人并未详述
Huh... His Grace does not go into details,
但请陛下不必担心 他亲笔写道
but...to allay Your Majesty's fears,he writes, in his own hand:
"臣祈求陛下不必担心 "
"I beseech Your Majesty to take in good part whatever promises"
"在目前情势下我所虚与委蛇对他们的许诺"
"I shall make to these rebels,
"而我事后将不受任何上述承诺之约束"
for surely I shall never keep any of them."
你们这帮不满之徒
Alas, you unhappy men.
什么愚蠢的怪念头蛊惑了你们
What fancy, what folly has led and seduced you
居然如此对待你们最高贵 最正直之王公君主
to make this most shameful rebellion against our most noble and righteous king and sovereign?
你不感觉羞耻吗 你怎能如此
Are you not ashamed?How can you do this,
怎么胆敢冒犯尔等天然 救主之君王
not only giving offence to your natural sovereign Lord
迫使我们与你们与你们交战
but giving us occasion to fight with you,
吾王热爱你等甚于王国任何其他地方
that have loved you more than any other part of the realm,
并始终像至亲好友般对待你们
and have always taken you for our best friends?
公爵大人 我们并无意冒犯国王陛下
Your Grace, we mean no offence to His Majesty.
但我们只是请愿 谦卑而且恳切地希望能送呈陛下
But we have a petition which we desire humbly to submit to him,
王国已经失去太多不应当失去的东西
for the restoration of many things which have gone amiss in this realm.
我们要求恢复我们的修道院 以及我们传统的权利
We demand the restoration of our abbeys and our ancient rights.
重造能重视民众的诉求之新国会
And a new Parliamentbe summoned to address the people's sincere grievances.
此刻我无法答复
I can decide nothing here.
但我提议休战
But I propose a truce,
在此期间 可请二位首领 前去当面向国王陈情
during which time two of your captains can take your petition and present it to His Majesty.
在他们回来之前我们保持休战
The truce to be maintained until they return.
达西勋爵 可否一叙？
My Lord Darcy, can we talk a moment?
达西勋爵
My Lord Darcy,
您应当比这里的任何人都更该报答陛下恩惠
you more than anyone here has cause to be grateful to the King for his bounty,
陛下也一直对大人信赖并寄予厚望
for the trust he reposes in you
而且依旧如此
and would like to repose in you still..
但我却发现您与这帮叛军沆瀣一气
And yet here I find you consorting with rebels and traitors.
从我内心深处 我过去以及将来都永远忠于吾王陛下
For my part I have been and always will be true to the King
我们的真命天子 我过去曾与吾王情同父子
our sovereign Lord, as I was to his father before him.
如您所言非虚 依旧忠诚于王
If you are as true and loyal as you say,
您大可向我们证明此事
then you can prove it to us
就是将叛军首领阿斯克的项上人头交来
by giving overyour Captain Mr. Aske into our hands.
大人 这我不愿也不会去做
Sir, that I cannot and will not do.
对于许诺坦诚相交之人
For a man who promises to be true to someone
背叛出卖才真可谓之叛徒
then betrays him may truly be called a traitor.
国王陛下驾到
His Majesty, the King!
- 夫人 - 陛下
- Madam. - Your Majesty.
臣妾看到陛下大为好转甚为欣慰
It makes me happy to see you so much improved.
寡人新得很好的治疗师
I have a good physician.
尽管如此 我还是希望
Nevertheless, I intend we shall visit the shrine
我们尽快去造访托马斯·柏克特神殿并致谢
of Sir Thomas Becket and give our thanks.
我已安排了其他事宜 而这我满怀希望 可以使您欢愉
I have arranged for something else which I hope,with all my heart, will make you very happy.
陛下 玛丽·都铎女士觐见
Your Majesty, the Lady Mary Tudor.
我恳求得到陛下祝福
I ask Your Majesty for His blessing.
我亲生女儿
My own daughter.
请允许我向珍王后陛下引见
May I present you to Her Majesty Queen Jane?
我记得你们当中有人曾热衷于提议处死我女儿
I remember, some of you were desirous that I should put this jewel to death!
有我在 你已经安全了
I've got you, your safe.
好好开心吧 玛丽
Be of good cheer, Mary.
从今往后 将不复再有针对你的敌意
For I swear nothing now will go against you.
继续
Continue!
- 你高兴吗 - 是的陛下
- Are you happy? - Yes, Your Majesty.
国王陛下已经同意给你在杭斯顿和格林威治宫安排居处
His Majesty has agreed to give you lodgings at Hampton Court and others at Greenwich Palace.
我都去看过 都很漂亮
I've seen them both; they're beautiful.
我对国王陛下和王后陛下感激不尽
I am very grateful to His Majesty and to you.
每个人都说我女儿纯真无邪
Everyone says my daughter is innocent,
说她未曾听说过任何污言秽语
that she doesn't know any unclean or foul speech.
你相信吗
Do you believe that?
你能相信任何人可以那么纯真无辜吗
Do you believe that anybody could be that innocent?
去查探一下
Go and find out.
玛丽女士
Lady Mary.
我必须对我当日行为道歉 期盼得到您的真心宽恕
I wanted to apologize for my behavior.I hope you can find it in your heart to forgive me.
我会试的 弗朗西斯爵士 基督要我们宽恕所有人
I will try, Sir Francis.Jesus asks us to forgive everyone.
- 你玩游戏吗 玛丽女士 - 是的
- Do you like games, Lady Mary? - Yes.
最近宫内流行一种新游戏 或许你会喜欢
There is a new game at court that you might enjoy.
是什么
What is it?
那叫做"舔阴" 乃是一种古老乡村活动
It's called cunnilingus. It's an old country practice.
- 怎么玩法？- 呃 你…
- How do you play it? - Well you...You...
我想你是在拿我取乐 弗朗西斯爵士
I think you're making fun of me, Sir Francis.
不可
No!
切莫冒犯于我
Noli Me Tangere
而今已非昔比
You can'touch me
乌鸦已变凤凰
For Caesar's I am
陛下宣见 拉尔夫·艾列克爵士 约翰·康斯特布尔先生
Your Majesty, Sir Ralph Ellerker and Mr. John Constable.
先生们 我且来问你们
Gentlemen, I ask you this:
世间是否还有王公保护你等安康和平长久如斯
What King has kept his subjects so long in wealth and peace?
治下对贵族与平民一视同仁
So ministered justice equally to high and low,
庇护尔等远离外敌
and protected you from all outward enemies?
我已阅尔等降书
I have read your submission.
你等首先伪称寻求维持信仰 现我告诉你们 先生们
Your first pretence is that you seek to maintain the faith.But I tell you now gentlemen,
没有比反叛更违背上帝诫令之举
that nothing is more contrary to God's commandment than rebellion.
针对你等王公暴力起事
Rising like madmen against your prince,
却丢弃田地荒芜 颗粒无收
leaving lands untilled and corn unsown is not
绝非尔等宣称忠良臣民所称行为
the behavior of the proper commonwealth you claim to be
陛下 我感觉被逼迫…
! Your Majesty I feel compelled.
噤声 你可是在觐见吾王陛下
Hush! You are before the King's Majesty.
你们恶意曲解我们对教会的行动
You make false claims about our intentions towards the church.
我们所做的完全出自约克郡与坎特伯雷教会
We have done nothing but what the clergy in Yorkand Canterbury
同意并完全符合上帝之圣言
agreed was in accordance with God's holy word.
上帝之圣言 先生们
God's holy word, gentlemen!
如何该看待你们的逆天而行？
So how can the simple people say the contrary?
宣称遵循上帝之诫令而其实一无所知
What presumption and madness is it of them to claim
或知之甚少是何等的臆断与疯狂
the knowledge of God's law when they are ignorant
又怎能了解自己的本分？
and less knowledgeable and should rather know their duty?
你们当该已见到我们
You have seen before, in Lincolnshire and elsewhere,
对林肯郡等地的临时赦免
how temperate and forgiving is our inclination.
反叛行为违背上帝意愿
Though rebellion is against God's will,
本王自心存怜悯 广施慈悲
I declare my intention through the pity and compassion of our princely heart
赦免所有罪人
to pardon all of you who have transgressed,
但限立即放下武器
on condition that you now lay down your arms.
沙福克公爵大人明日将前赴约克郡
His Grace the Duke of Suffolkwill come North again to Yorkshire
与尔等安排会面讲和
to moderate with you and make peace
并见证你们遣散诸等事宜
and see you disbanded.
再见 先生们
Good day, gentlemen.
公爵大人
Your Grace?
公爵大人应该知道 我们求恩巡礼武装
Your Grace should know our army of pilgrims will not disperse
绝不会仅仅一个宽恕的许诺而就此遣散
just for the promise of a pardon.
求恩行动远远未了
Our pilgrimage is not over.
我当然知道 也与陛下谈过
I do know.And I have told the King.
这也是派我来进一步商谈的原因
That is why he has given me permission to negotiate with you further.
满怀诚信
in good faith.
在我们请愿书内容的基础上？
On the basis of our petition?
正是
Yes.
公爵阁下是否坦诚宣誓？
Does Your Grace have some token of this "good faith"?
难道你不相信我的话
You don't trust my word?
这不是为了我 是为了阿斯克首领
Not for me, for our Captain Mr. Aske.
他乃律师出身
He's a lawyer.
此乃出自陛下亲笔的书面允诺
Here is a promise.in his Majesty's own hand,
内容坦诚 公允 合理 因为吾王挚爱其子民
to deal with you openly, fairly and reasonably,as his loving subjects.
我们感激陛下恩典
We are grateful and abundant to His Majesty
晚安 先生们
Good night, Gentlemen
此函交予兰开夏郡传令官 立即送去
This is for the Lancashire Herald.See that it is dispatched immediately.
康斯特布尔先生
Mr. Constable...
我恳求您切莫相信克伦威尔先生
I beg you, do not put your trustin Mr. Cromwell.
感谢上帝 陛下 您今天真是宽宏大量
I thank God and Your Majesty for your great mercy today.
我认为您是最仁慈的君主
I think you are the kindest of rulers,
我全心全意希望世人皆知
and I wish with all my heart the world knew it.
世人只是选择他们想听的而已 珍
The world chooses what it wants to know, Jane.
但您可改变世人心意
But you can change its mind!
我恳求您恢复并保留修道院
I beg you to restore and keep the abbeys.
珍
Jane...
想世人所想 倾听一下你的人民和你的内心
Think what the world will think.That you listened to your people and to your heart.
珍
Jane...
我曾经告诫过你
I've told you once before:
切勿干预我的事务
Don't to meddle with my affairs.
你是否记得上任王后发生何事？
Do you remember what happened to the late Queen?
知道
Yes...
我爱你甚过她 也甚过于凯瑟琳
I love you more than her.More even than Catherine.
千万别恃宠过度
Don't spoil it.
(西班牙属荷兰)
波尔红衣主教大人
Cardinal Pole.
我是迭伊哥·胡尔塔多·门多萨
My name is Diego Hurtado de Mendoza
这些先生们乃吾皇查尔斯五世陛下之顾问
and these gentlemen are all advisers to His Imperial Majesty, King Charles V.
先生们
Sirs,
我随身带来教皇陛下使节命封在此
I carry this letter of legatine authority from his Holiness Pope Paul.
请坐
Shall we be seated?
我们听说您要前来 但请恕我们
We were aware, Eminence, that you were on your way here.But, forgive me,
尚不了解您此番前来的使命
we remaina little unsure as to the exact nature of your mission.
我相信你们都已了解全英爆发之反王起义
I am sure you are aware of the risings which have taken place across England against the King,
尤其针对邪教徒克伦威尔及其党羽
that heretic Cromwell and all his sect.
我们得知此事的一些情报 我们当然很关注此事
We have heard some information, certainly. And naturally we are intrigued.
这些起义正是我们重还英格兰
These popular risings are the greatest chance that we may ever have
真正信仰的绝佳机会
to restore the true religion to England,
但是这些我国信徒同胞需要支援
but the faithful people of my country need support.
你我每个人 门多萨先生
Each of us, senor Mendoza,
都需要以各自的方式 去鼓励 持续发展壮大这股力量
in our own way must encourage the risings to continue and to grow in strength.
即使这意味着最终导致颠覆国王吗 而并非他的邪恶阁员
Even if that means the overthrow of the King himself,not just his wicked council?
正是如此
Yes.
我们可以大胆的如此设想
We can imagine such an outcome without fear
因为另有位怀有真正信仰的王位合法继承人
for there is another, close to the throne,with a legitimate claim and a true faith:
玛丽女士
The Lady Mary.
如果她不
If not her,
还有一位天主教徒具有登基之合法性
there is still another Catholic with a legitimate claim.
一位先于都铎王朝就统治过王国的安茹王朝后裔
A scion of the Plantagenets,who ruled before the Tudors,
会很乐意登基大统
and would gladly rule after them.
您指谁 红衣主教大人
Of whom do you speak, Your Eminence?
我指我本人 门多萨先生
I speak of myself, senor Mendoza.
拉尔夫 约翰 我们都在为你们祈祷
Ralph...John! We have waited and prayed for your
希望你们安全返回 谢天谢地
safe return.Thank God! Thank God!
国王很仁慈 许诺大赦天下
The King in his mercy has offered us a general pardon!
并派沙福克公爵前来
He is also sending the Duke of Suffolk to negotiate and treat with us,
在我们请愿书的基础上无先决条件的与我们磋商
without preconditions and on the basis of our demands.
- 当真？- 是的 我相信国王的真诚
- Is it true? - I trust the King's good faith and mercy
有书面为证 我们将再次在此会晤
and here's the proof of it.We are to meet again here.
你未发一言 约翰
You have not said anything yet, John.
你是否与拉尔夫爵士意见相左
Is it because you do not agree with Sir Ralph?
对 我无法相信
No, I cannot agree with him.
我怎么相信 那个邪恶的克伦威尔依然在当政
How should I agree when I think that devil Cromwell has such a hold over the King
这些许诺就一文不值
that I account these promises to be utterly worthless!
你认为我们不该和他们商谈吗
You don't think we should meet with them?
我想目前暂且不谈 我们应当戳穿他们的谎言
No, I don't. We should expose their lies.
来一次全面出击 夺取整个英国北部地区
Call a general muster,take the entire of the North
届时再行谈判
and only then condescend to a meeting.
你凭什么认为他们的话不可置信呢
Why are you so sure that their word is not to be trusted?
- 看看这个 - 那是什么
- Because of this. - What's that?
一封克伦威尔写过约克郡士绅贵人信件的复制件
A copy of a letter from Cromwell to the Yorkshire gentry.
我给你念念这些
I'll read some of it to you.
"这些叛乱者有望和平遣散
"There is hope they may disperse peacefully,
"但仍能死灰复燃 再度非法聚集
"but if these rebels continue with their illegal assemblies
"除非以雷霆手段给与严酷镇压
"and their defiance then their rebellion will be crushed so forcibly
"以达威慑所有臣民之功
"that their example shall be fearful to all subjects
"唯有如此世界方可持久"
so long as the world does endure."
"唯有如此世界方可持久" 先生们
"So long as the world does endure", gentlemen.
但其实他们镇压不了我们 所以沙福克公爵才被迫来谈判
But the truth is they cannot crush us.And that is why the Duke is forced to negotiate.
但这么明显的可疑之处你竟然都置之不理
This sure sign of their deviousness does not impress you then?...
我说我们先不解除警备
I say we do not stop our vigilance.
但准备做好会谈准备
But prepare for our meeting,
明确我们的立场
clarify our positions
强化我们的要求
and strengthen our arguments
同时让我们的教会负责人背书
and have our Church leaders endorse them.
- 我们不必恐惧 约翰 我们就要接近胜利了 - 我知道 但是…
- Why should we fear, John, when we are about God's work? - I know we are but...
我只希望我们当中 或我们的子孙后代 不会以此刻为憾
I only hope that none of us, nor our grandchildren-ever live to regret this moment.
祝你此行顺利 马到成功
I wanted to wish you every success for your journey
安抚好那些叛军
and conference with the rebels.
谢陛下
I am grateful to Your Majesty.
你知道我更期望和平
You know I desire more than anything else a peaceful remedy.
我许诺你可根据情势自主定夺
You have my permission to prolong the truce for as long as necessary.
你也可给与那些反叛分子大赦 但头目们除外
You may also affirm my general pardon to all the rebels. Except their leaders.
我依然希望你抓获并绞死他们
I want them brought to you still,with halters around their necks!
陛下知道这些叛军 无疑很明显归罪于克伦威尔大臣阁下
Your Majesty knows the rebels, no doubt unjustly, blame Master Cromwell
在诸多方面 他们反复重申要求将其革职查办
for many of their actions.Repeatedly they ask for his removal and punishment.
这方面我该如何回复他们
What should I tell them?
你知道这个吗 查尔斯
You know what this is, Charles?
来自新世界的水果
Fruit from the New World.
芳林新时催旧叶 流水前波让后波
New things come in.Everything changes.
我很喜欢纳新
I have a great appetite for novelty.
你可随意应付
Tell them what you like.
先生们
Gentlemen,
我读了你们的请愿书 在诸多条款之中
I have read your new petition.Among other articles, you ask
你们要求设立召开特别国会会议
for the setting up of a special convocation or Parliament
并要求保证会议不受国王喜恶所左右
to debate without fear or his Majesty's displeasure
质询恶行 王室特权
questions of heresy,the royal supremacy,
维护信仰
and maintenance of the faith.
我先可告知你们 国王非常赞同这个要求
I can tell you now that the King has graciously conceded to your request.
特别国会将不在威斯敏斯特举行
A special parliament will be summoned to be held not far away at Westminster
而是在此地 约克郡来决议所以事宜
but here in York, to debate and decide on all these questions.
谢谢 我们还要求废除并焚毁那些路德
Thank you. We have asked for the heresies of Luther,Wycliffe and Tyndaleto
威克力夫 丁道尔等人邪教传说
be annulled and destroyed.
我们要求惩处异教徒主教以及教众
We have asked that the heretics,bishops and temporal, be punished.
克伦威尔 奥德利 理查德·瑞奇爵士 因在国土之内玷污信仰
That Cromwell, Audley, Sir Richard Rich be punished as subverters of the good laws of this realm
并传播邪教受到惩处
and maintainers of false sects.
这个并非我可以决定
That is not for me to decide
不管我对此有何感受
whatever my true feelings.
但此项问题正是需要特别国会去制宪并决议的
But such questions are exactly what the special Parliament will be constituted to decide.
此特别国会是否可以就教皇辖权
Is it possible that this Parliament can also debate the question of papal obedience,
灵魂救治 玛丽女士王位合法继承权等事宜进行表决
touching the cure of souls,and the legitimacy of the Lady Mary?
是的 阿斯克先生 我可保证上述重大事宜
Yes, Mr. Aske.I can guarantee that all these great matters
均可提交特别国会决议 不受国王喜恶所左右
can be put before the Parliament without fear or favor.
国王是否还愿意实施大赦呢
And the King is still willing to offer a general pardon?
是的 但是我说此事略带踌躇
Yes. I say that with hesitation.
国王越是了解此番起义的缘由
The more His Majesty understands the causes of this uprising,
求恩者们对国王本人与其统治的忠心
and the loyalty of the pilgrims to his person and rule,
就会越发乐意大发慈悲
the more is he persuaded to show clemency.
还有一重大事宜 公爵大人应当知道
There is one other great matter. Your Grace knows that we demand
我们强烈要求镇压修道院的行动应该中止 甚至恢复修道院
that the suppressed abbeys should stand or be restored.
这是我们的重点所在
This is our sticking point.
我们将永远为之献身战斗来维护我们信仰的场所
We were always determined to fight and die for the maintenance of our religious houses.
对此我所能说的是 所有摧毁修道院的行为都将停止
What I can say about that is that all further destruction of the abbeys
留待国会议案处置
will cease until Parliament meets.
国会也将就其他修道院是否恢复 何时恢复进行议案
It will then be up to Parliament to decide if and when the others will be restored.
回家吧 放下武器
Go home and put aside your arms.
通过我们这次起义 起义的力量 我相信我们已经达到了
By standing together and by standing strong, I believe we have achieved
我们求恩巡礼目的所能取得的最大结果
as much as we could have gained when we first took up this great pilgrimage of ours.
快到圣诞节了 回家去欢庆我主耶稣基督之诞辰
It is almost Christmas. Go home and celebrate the birth of our Lord Jesus Christ
我们感谢上帝 也感谢吾王陛下
We thank God as we thank the King's Majesty
我们达到了要求一切 却并未血风腥雨
that all this has been achieved without bloodshed.
有请国王传令官
Please listen to the King's herald.
吾王陛下 亨利八世
"His Gracious Majesty King Henry VIII
特此谕令大赦
"hereby pardons by royal command all those subjects
所有参与非法叛乱之臣民
"who have transgressed and risen in unlawful rebellion."
因此 我要求所有人就地遣散 回家 放下武器
I therefore ask everyone of you to disperse, go home and put aside your arms.
我们已经确定我们的信仰得到了维护 没有被毁灭
Firm in the knowledge that our faith is to be maintained and not destroyed!
这是什么 丈夫
What is it, husband?
相信是来自国王
I believe it's from the King.
那信啥内容
What does it say?
父亲
Father?!
"可信赖及热爱之罗伯特·阿斯克先生台鉴
"My trusty and well beloved Aske. I am informed that,"notwithstanding
"我获悉尽管您参与近期发生之叛乱
your offences committed against us"in the late rebellion attempted in those parts,
"却能迷途知返 并决心做忠实子民
"you are now at heart repentant."And since you are determined to be a faithful subject,
"我们热切期望与您会谈
we have conceived a great desire to speak with you..."
- 父亲 - 别吵 孩子们 听你父亲说
- Father! - Hush, children, hush! Listen to your father...
"听你亲口陈述整桩事变之来龙去脉
"And to hear from your mouth the whole circumstance and beginning of that matter."
国王想跟我谈话 你能相信吗
The King wants to speak with me. Can you believe it?
"鉴于我们已经深知您是位忠臣良民
"I therefore order you, as our true and faithful subject, as we now repute you,
"现我命你圣诞期间前来宫廷
" to come to court for Christmastide.
"此行不宜让别人知晓
"You are not to let anyone know,but you will use such plainness
"相信你坦荡真诚 我们甚为倚重
and frankness in all things we shall demand of you,
"或许给予进一步嘉奖"
that we may have cause to reward you even further."
这里另有附注保障
There is a credence attached
"您赴宫廷之约来去安全
saying that "You shall safe come and safe go from court,
"应与圣诞节第12日回家"
returning before the twelfth day of Christmas."
我只是想确定这是真的…
Just make sure that he means to honor
您真的相信沙福克公爵在邓卡斯特代表陛下的那些承诺？
the promises Lord Suffolk made on his behalf.
难道国王已经将此事作为心中大事不明摆着吗？
Is it not obvious that the King has taken this matterto his heart?
这信件应当是由他亲笔书就
This is a letter written in his own hand.
您太乐意轻信 这次我不去了
You are still too trusting. I would not go now.
他们许诺了可以安全返回
But there is a promise of safe return.
诺言可以被打破
Promises can be broken.
康斯特布尔先生 国王的金口玉言
Mr. Constable, the promisesof a King are worth a great deal
远非寻常草木之人言语
more than the promises of ordinary folk.
我们应当这么做 我将安排联程驿马
Here's what we shall do:I will arrange to lay post horses
从这里一直到伦敦
all the way between here and London,
如果一旦发生意外 阿斯克先生
so that if God forbid, Mr. Aske,
你被捕入狱 或被恶意对待
you were imprisoned or otherwise badly treated,
我会立即得到消息并聚众重新起事 要求释放您
I will hear about it straight away,and raise the people again for your deliverance.
谢谢达西大人
Thank you Lord, that's it.